またそんな顔して 唇噛み締めて
mata sonna kao wo shite
There you go, making that face again,
biting onto your lips.
kuchibiru kamishimete
弱さを隠してるけど
yowasa wo kakushiteru kedo
You're hiding your weak side,
sono hitomi no oku
but deep in those eyes,
その瞳の奥 うずくまる君が
uzukumaru kimi ga
I can see you cowering.
本当の心なら
honto no kokoro nara
If you had a true heart,
思って 泣いて 一人で 不安で
omotte, naite, hito yonde, fuwande
you would care, cry, call for someone and worry.
なんで 痛いの 持ってんだ
nande itai no mottenda
Why are you holding onto the pain?
僕に そっと 預けてよ
boku ni sotto azukete yo
Share some of it with me.
直ぐじゃ無理と思うのならば
sugu ja muri to omou no naraba
If you don't think it's possible right away,
少しずつでいい
sukoshi zutsu de ii
you can do it slowly, bit by bit.
翼の無い僕等はきっと
tsubasa no nai bokura kitto
We don't have wings,
tobenai toki mitsuketeru dake
but I'm sure we're only finding times that we can't fly.
飛べないと 決め付けてるだけ
koe no kagiri kimi wo yobu yo
I'll call for you to the limits of my voice
声の限り君を呼ぶよ 迷わないように
mayowanai you ni
so that you won't get lost.
フワリ心舞い上がれ あの風に乗せて
fuwari kokoro maiagare
Soar up to the sky with your gentle heart,
ano kaze ni nosete issei erose
ride on that wind, and get it all at once.
Natsume
Yuujinchou
It's so cool now.
すっかり涼しくなったな
ああ 山の紅葉はもっときれいだろうな
Yeah, the maple trees on the mountain are a lot prettier too.
Let's go to the Futaba Dam sometime soon.
近いうちに 双葉ダムへ行こうか
お いいね
Sounds good.
I'll bring along some lewd stuff then.
じゃあ おれなんかちょっぴりエッチなもの持って来る係
おお ってか何で
Why?
Don't bother with him, Natsume.
乗るな 夏目
I'll bring snacks.
俺はおやつ係やるわ
I'll bring drinks, then.
じゃあ 俺はお飲物
You take care of the sandwiches, Natsume.
夏目はおサンドイッチな
Sorry, I can't make lunches on my days off.
悪いけど 休日の弁当はちょっと
What are you talking about?
何言ってんだよ 塔子さんに頼んでみろよ
Try asking Touko-san.
I'm sure she'll be happy.
きっと喜ぶぞ
And I'll be happy too!
で 俺も嬉しい
Touko's sandwiches!
塔子さんのおサンドイッチ
You think so?
そうだろうか
Five Day Mark
Later, Natsume.
じゃあな 夏目
Yeah, see you later.
うん また
A Youkai...
妖怪が 妖怪を食べてる
is eating another Youkai!
I smell a human.
人の匂い
You saw me, didn't you?
我を見たな
I'll eat you.
食ってやる 食ってやる
I'll eat you!
放せ
Let go!
Running is futile!
逃げても無駄だ 食ってやるぞ 小僧
I'll eat you, boy!
I'm coming to eat you!
食いにいくぞ
ただいま
I'm back.
Welcome back, Takashi-kun.
お帰り 貴志君
あ どうしたの 顔色悪いわ
What's wrong? You look pale.
あ そうですか 別に何も
Really? It's nothing.
あ 大変 焦げちゃう
Oh no! It'll burn!
You're back, Natsume?
夏目 帰ったか
Nyanko-sensei.
ニャンコ先生
うむ いいにおいだ
What a nice smell.
今夜はイカのフライだな
We're having fried squid tonight.
イカはいかが
How's the squid?
Cats can't eat squid.
猫はイカ食べちゃいけないんだぞ
I told you, I'm not a cat!
猫ではないと言っとろうが
うん どうした 夏目 その痣は
What's with that mark, Natsume?
S-Sensei!
せん 先生
お お前
Y-You...
腕に呪いを受けたな
You got a curse on your arm, didn't you?
Curse?
呪い
It's nothing to laugh about, you idiot!
笑いごとか 阿呆
あ 痛
How dare he lay his hands on my prey? It's positively inexcusable!
全く この私の獲物に手を付けるとは けしからん
And he's going to eat you?
しかも食うだと
Normally, I'd be grateful,
普段ならありがたいが
今の私ではそいつに横取りされかねんからな
but I simply can't allow him to get you before I do.
Hey...
あのな
All right,
しょうがないな
let's call someone else to be your bodyguard in my place.
私に代わる用心棒として 誰かを呼び出すか
呼び出すって
Call them?
We'll use the Book of Friends.
友人帳を使うのさ
The Book of Friends?
友人帳 そんなことできるのか
We can do that?
Reiko boasted about it before.
レイコが自慢げに話しておった
Like this?
こんな感じか
That's good. Next, put that white cloth on and then stand right in the middle of the characters.
いいだろう
次に白い布を羽織って 陣の真ん中に立て
It's to substitute a white robe.
白衣の代用だ
You can't call them unless you know their name and how they look,
顔と名前を知らねば呼べぬから
so let's try to call Misuzu from before.
この間の三筱を呼び出してみるか
Natsume, place the Book of Friends and the mirror beside each other and then drop some blood on it.
夏目 鏡と友人帳を置いて 血を落とせ
Blood?
血
Normally, they'd want a fingernail.
本来なら生爪の一枚も欲しいところだ
Don't think you can deal with Ayakashi without some compensation.
妖相手に 代償なしで済むと思うなよ
Let's do it, Natsume.
やるぞ 夏目
Okay.
One who would protect me,
我を護りしものよ
come forth to me.
我が元へ来れ
Your name is...
汝の名
Misuzu.
三筱
It has been a while, Natsume-dono.
夏目殿 お久しぶりでございますな
I'm sorry I couldn't return your name last time, Misuzu.
この前は名前を返しそびれて 悪かったな
三筱 力を貸してほしいことがある
I need your power.
Please help me for a while.
少し付き合ってくれ
ふん よろしいでしょう
Very well.
It's about this.
これなんだけど
It spread out more than before.
あ さっきより広がってる
Oh? A curse mark.
おや 呪いの印
これはまずい
This is not good.
I am not familiar with curses, though.
だが私は呪いに詳しくはございません
I will send for someone else.
代わりの者を寄越しましょう
助かる
That'd be a huge help.
しかし夏目殿
However, Natsume-dono, you should not show any weaknesses to Ayakashi.
妖に弱い心を見せてはなりませぬよ
妖は人の心の弱さや影を映す
Ayakashi attack people through their weaknesses and shadows.
Loneliness can serve as compensation for Ayakashi.
寂しさを妖で埋め合わせておいでで
You're being quite rude to your master, Misuzu.
三筱 主にいい態度だな
あまり調子に乗るなよ
Don't get too ahead of yourself.
And this coming from you, Madara?
よく言うわ 斑
I can't believe you can call yourself his bodyguard when he has some mark now.
印など付けさせておいて 用心棒が聞いて呆れる
What?!
何
Natsume-dono, please forget that cat doll and call upon me anytime.
夏目殿 そんな猫だるま
見限られたらいつでも申されよう
I will protect you.
私がお守りしよう
Hey! Who's a cat doll?!
こら 誰が猫だるまだ
Damned rocking horse!
木馬野郎
Well then, I shall call for Hinoe.
では 丙を呼んで参ります
Hey!
Hey, what? Did he say Hinoe?
おい 何 丙だと
You know her?
知ってるのか 先生
Ah, she's...
あ ああ あいつは
Reiko! Reiko!
レイコ レイコ
She's...
ああ あいつは
You've finally called for me...
やっと我を呼んだか
麗しのレイコ
My lovely Reiko!
おお その蔑むような目
Oh, those scornful eyes,
those thin lips...
薄ら笑いが似合う唇
What's with your hair?
どうしたのだ その髪は
Did those humans bully you again?
また人間に嫌がらせされたのかい
あんな口惜しいや人間ども
Damn those rotten humans!
Shall I curse to death all the ones who touched you?
お前に触れるものは皆 この丙が祟り殺してくれようか
ん 胸がない
You have no breasts.
な なんと
Wh-What?
A man?!
男
She's a big Reiko lover.
あいつは重度のレイコ好きだ
How disgusting.
気色の悪い
And she hates men.
そして男嫌いだ
うん その声は
That voice...
斑か
Madara?
何で分かった
How'd you know?
なんだ そのへちゃむくれ姿は
What's with that small, furry form?
Did you want Reiko to like you that much?
そうまでしてレイコにウケたいのか
落ちつかんか 丙
Calm down, Hinoe!
Natsume's getting scared.
夏目がドン引きしとるぞ
So,
で そのレイコの偽物は一体なんだい
who's this fake Reiko?
I'm her grandson, Takashi.
夏目レイコの孫 貴志です
Grandson? What about Reiko?
孫 レイコはどうした
She died a long time ago.
遠の昔に他界した
I see...
そうか
What a short life...
なんと短い
That's why I hate getting attached to people.
だから好かんのだ 人は
Don't get closer to me, you damned man!
寄るな 男め
使ってください
Please use it.
You're crying for Reiko-san, right?
レイコさんのために 泣いてくれてるんでしょう
Excuse me.
いや 失礼した
Misuzu-dono had said that Natsume called for me...
三筱殿が夏目が呼んでいると
つい興奮してしまったよ
So I got a bit excited.
What are you doing?
何をする
It's the Five Day Mark.
五日印だね
Five Day Mark?
五日印
動けない妖ものが近くを通った奴に印をつけるんだ
This Ayakashi cannot move, and so he places marks on people passing by.
For five days, the mark will comsume their life force,
印は五日間かけて そやつの生気を吸い尽くしたり
主の所へ引き寄せて 食べたり
and will draw them to the owner of the mark to be eaten.
By repeating that, the owner of the mark will gain the power to be free.
それを繰り返して 印主は何時か自由になる力を得るのさ
That's strange.
変だな
I can't remember which way I went.
どこから入ったか 思い出せない
You probably went on some path humans can not take,
恐らく人には通れぬ道に入って
and met the owner of that mark.
そこで印主に会ったのだろうな
Geez... It'll be bothersome, but I'll look into it.
やれやれ 面倒だが 調べといてやるから
Go home for now.
今日はもう帰りな
厄介なことになったな
I got myself involved in some bad business.
What's that?
なんだ
It's an not an Ayakashi.
妖ものではないな
Ah, this might be nice.
これいいかもね
あら どうしたの
What's wrong with your arm?
その腕
It got scraped on a tree branch.
あ 木の枝で引っ掻いちゃって
大したことないです
It's nothing serious.
My, my, it'll be bad if it festers.
まあまあまあ 化膿したら大変
It's okay! There aren't any problems!
大丈夫です 問題なしです
ほら
See?
I'm fine!
元気ですから
No, show m-
だめよ 見せて頂
いってきます
I'm going now.
Damn, it's really spreading.
まいったな やっぱり広がってる
What's with this shadow? It's like Merry.
なんだか この影メリーさんみたいだ
Who's this Merry?
メリーさん なんだそれは
It's a horror story where some unknown creature gets closer and closer to you.
得体の知れないものが 少しずつ近づいてくるっていう怪談だよ
You get a phone call,
電話がかかってくるんだ
私メリーさん 今門の前にいるのって
and they say, "I'm Merry. I'm at the front gate now."
しばらくすると また電話が鳴る
After a while, another call comes.
出てみると
When you pick it up,
they say, "I'm Merry. I'm at the front door."
私メリーさん 今玄関の前にいるの
Does it have something to do with this mark?
この痣と何か関係があるのか
What should I do?
どうしよう
You have the same face as Reiko, so don't make such a pathetic expression.
レイコと同じ顔なのに しけた面をお見せでないよ
Hinoe.
丙
I found out who the owner of the mark is.
印主の正体が分かったよ
It's a powerful evil spirit that's been sealed away for a long time.
長年封印されてる強力な邪鬼だ
It uses the mark to hunt its prey.
印を使って獲物を狩り じわじわと力を蓄えて
Bit by bit, it stores its power.
It seems that if it eats one more, the seal will be broken.
どうやら後一人食えば封印が解けるようだ
One more? You mean me?
後一人って 俺のことか
That's right.
ああ そして力を取り戻しつつある邪鬼は
And the evil spirit, unable to wait to restore its power, sends out a shadow.
待ちきれずに 影を飛ばしてきた
The shadow will suck the life from you through the mark, and it'll be able to move faster and faster.
影はお前の印から生気を吸い取ってどんどん動きが速くなる
It's still slow now, and was finally able to find your house.
今はまだの鈍間で やっと家を探り当てたところだけどね
お前 あいつに触れられたら 死ぬよ
You'll die if it touches you.
You're huge, sensei!
先生 でか
むぅ 呪いの余波で妖力が安定せんわい
My power isn't stable because of the effects of the curse.
Damn it! Damn it! Damn it!
くそ くそ くそ
Stop it, you idiot!
止めろ ばか
Takashi-kun?
貴志君
Are you back, Takashi-kun?
貴志君 帰ったの
あら
That's strange, I thought I heard his voice.
おかしいわね 声がしたと思ったのに
Should I eat that shadow?
あの影 私が食ってしまおうか
No one without the mark can touch it.
印のない奴には 触れもしないよ
It doesn't matter. The Five Day Mark will only last four more days.
まあ いいじゃないか
五日印の効力は後四日
You just have to run away for that period.
その間逃げ回ってればいいのさ
I just need to run away?
逃げ切ればいいんだな 後四日
Just four more days...
Yeah.
I don't want to worry them.
この人達には心配かけたくない
But...
でも 一緒にいると何が起こるか分からないし
I don't know what may happen if I'm with them.
If I camp out and return by morning,
野宿して 朝こっそり戻れば
Touko-san shouldn't notice.
塔子さんにも気付かれないさ
Damn that Merry!
くそ メリーさんめ ついに家に入って来た
It went into the house!
I shouldn't go back home.
もう帰らない方がいい
Fortunately, it's a long weekend tomorrow.
幸い 明日から連休だ
Did you fall in love with some foreigner or something, Natsume?
夏目 外国人に恋でもしたのか
How international!
インターナショナル
あ 塔子さんですか 貴志です
Touko-san?
It's Takashi.
I'll be staying at my friend's house for the next three days.
今日から三日間 友達の家に泊まります
No.
いえ はい
Yes.
Ah, no. Whose house? Well...
あ いえ 誰の家ってそれは
あ あの みんなが待ってるんで すいません
Ah, everyone's waiting! Sorry!
Takashi-kun?
貴志君
I wonder if she'll worry.
心配かけちゃうかな 塔子さんに
I'll cause her trouble if I'm there, though.
でも 俺がいたら迷惑が
You're not like Reiko.
お前はレイコと違うね
You like humans, don't you?
お前は人が好きなんだね
I didn't like them when I was small.
小さい頃は苦手だったんだ
But after meeting kind people, I learned what kindness was.
でも 優しい人たちに出会えて 優しさを知って
I didn't want to run away anymore.
逃げたくないって思った
俺も優しくなりたいって 思ったんだ
I wanted to become kind too.
You're a man, so what's with the lame talk?
男のくせに 甘ちゃんなことを
You've got that right.
全くだ
Well, sorry!
悪かったな
It happened again.
まただよ
Geez, it'll just be this once, but how would you like having a servant to protect you?
やれやれ では今回限りの式を
お前に付けて 守らせるのはどうだ
式
A servant?
A creature of light that can expel the darkness.
影を払える系譜のものだよ
I will teach you how to summon one.
その呼び出し方を教えてやる
It'll be tough, so do you want to do it?
きついけど やるかい
With your energy, it'll be a one-shot battle.
その体力では一発勝負だ
Either a big one will show up, or a useless little one.
大物が出るか
役立たずの小物が出るか
Thank you, Hinoe.
ありがとう 丙
Why?! Why do you look like Reiko, yet you're a man?!
なぜだ
レイコに似てるのに 何で男なんだ
It looks painful.
辛いようだな
Rest a bit before the real thing.
本番前に少し休め 夏目
Guess I'll go get some fish.
魚でも捕って来てやるか
I want... to go back home...
帰りたい 家へ
It chased after me?
追って来たのか 巻物は
Where's the scroll?
I'll eat you, boy!
食ってやるぞ 小僧
I won't let you!
そうはさせるか
Sensei!
先生
Natsume!
夏目
Use it!
使え
I summon thee from the paths of light,
日 通りし道より来たれ
you who expels the darkness.
影 祓うもの
It's here?
来たか
うわ ちっさ
It's tiny!
Is that your servant?
それがお前の式か
Sensei...
先生 元に戻ったのか
I'm back to normal?
Yeah, it's all over.
ああ 終わったよ
Your mark is gone as well.
お前の印も消えている
I see.
そうか
Thank goodness.
よかった
Thank goodness, nothing.
よくないよ
Watching you, all I could see was your desire to protect important things,
お前を見ていて 思ったよ
大事なものを守りたいとか 迷惑をかけたくないとか
and not wanting to cause trouble for others.
All those kinds of feelings.
そんな気持ちばっかりだ
I hate people who don't treasure themselves.
自分を大切にできない奴は 大嫌いだよ
Sorry.
ごめん
Well done!
いやいや お見事
I had you tested, Natsume-dono.
夏目殿を試させていただいた
A test to see whether I should entrust my name to a human child or not.
人の子などに私の名前を預けておいてよいものなのかを
A test?
試す
I'm the one that made the path to lead you to the evil spirit.
かえるを使って 奴の所へ導いたのは私ですよ
Misuzu! You...
三筱 お前
食われるようなら それまでだ
If you were eaten, then that would have been it.
I would then take the Book of Friends for myself.
その時は 友人帳は私が頂こうかと
What?!
なんだと
What's your decision?
判定は
Unfit.
ふさわしくない
However, you're interesting.
しかし面白い
I like you, Natsume-dono.
気に入った 夏目殿
I shall entrust my name to you for a while.
今しばらくは名前を預けましょう
I don't terribly hate having my name called.
名を呼ばれるのも嫌いじゃない
Thank you.
ありがとう
I don't mind being called by you, either.
私も 夏目にだったら 呼ばれてやってもよい
If you ever find yourself in despair from humans, come to me anytime.
夏目 人間に嫌気がさしたら
いつでも私の所へおいで
Takashi-kun!
貴志君
Where'd you go?!
どこいってたの
I told you so many times to give me the contact information!
連絡先を教えてって あんなに言ったのに
I-I'm sorry.
す すいません
Sit over there!
ちょっとそこにお座りなさい
Yes!
はい
Just how worried do you think I was?
一体どれほど心配したと思ってるの
I don't mind you staying at your friend's house,
お友達の家に泊まるのは構わないわ
but you have to tell me where!
でも 居場所を教えてくれなきゃ
What'll I do if something happens?
もしものことがあったらどうするの
I was worrying all night!
もう私一晩中心配で心配で
I didn't even get one wink of sleep!
一睡もできなかったんだから
I'm back.
帰って来たんだ 僕の家に
Back at my home.
Are you listening, Takashi-kun?!
聞いてるの貴志君
Ah, yes! I'm listening.
あ はい 聞いてます
Back at this kind and warm house, where I live with my precious family.
優しく暖かい
僕の大切な人たちと暮らすこの家へ
色づく 西空に
hi no tsukurishi zora ni
On that day where the sky was ablaze,
差し込む一筋の陽
sashikomu hitosuji no hi
and rays of light were piercing through,
yuudachi no ameagari ni
the evening rain had stopped,
夕立の雨上がりに
気付く夏の匂い
kizuku natsu no nioi
I noticed the scent of summer,
ひしめく光が照らす
hishimeku hikari ga terasu
and the crowded, shining lights.
想いに耳を澄ませば
omoi ni mimi wo sumaseba
If I turned my ear to my thoughts,
聴こえし友の面影
kikoeshi tomo no omokage
I could hear traces of my dear friends.
夏夕空 薫り立つ
natsu yuuzora kawarirazu
The summer evening sky
鮮やかな過ぎ去りし日々
azayaka na sugisarishi hibi
and the vivid passing days were just the same,
心のまま笑いあった
kokoro no mama warai atta
and so I laughed; it was just like
あの夏の思い出よ
ano natsu no omoide yo
my memory of that summer.
Next Time on
Natsume Yuujinchou
Autumn Banquet
A long night in autumn.
秋の夜長 賑やかな祭り 空を彩る花火
A lively festival.
Fireworks coloring the sky.
The kind people I met in this city are here.
この町で出会った優しい人たちがいる
彼らのために俺は 何かしてあげられたのかな
Was I able to do something for them?